Markham Starr collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2. 2015 accrual: Against the Tide, Down On The Farm, In History's Wake, and Voices From The Waterfront photographs, March 26, 2005 through December 4, 2013, afc2013031_dc002; 841 TIFF, 4 pdf, 4 xls, and 1 m2t
  - Subseries 1. Against the Tide: The Commercial Fishermen of Point Judith RI files, March 26, 2005 through December 2, 2013, 411 TIFF, 1 pdf, 1 xls
    - North Star heads in under a swarm of gulls after emptying her three trap sites, April 30, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      North Star heads in under a swarm of gulls after emptying her three trap sites. Tom Hoxsie has one trap on the outside of the west wall of the Harbor of Refuge, one off of East Village, and one on the inside of the East Wall.
    - Anthony Richards brings the scallop dredge aboard the Njord at night, January 18, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Anthony Richards brings the scallop dredge aboard the Njord at night. All fishing offshore takes place around the clock, with fishermen catching what sleep they can between haulbacks. On this boat, with only two men, it makes for exhausting trips.
    - Bughunter at dock., November 11, 2005, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Linda Marie heads out to sea for a day of trawling with Block Island in the background and Tom Hoxsie's west wall fish trap gear in the foreground, May 8, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Wilie Fox III gillnetting in Block Island Sound, June 11, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Wilie Fox III gillnetting in Block Island Sound. There were only a handful of gillnetters operating out of Point Jude at this time.
    - The Elizabeth Helen hauling back outside of Block Island on a day trip groundfishing, June 11, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The Elizabeth Helen hauling back outside of Block Island on a day trip groundfishing. This vessel was lost at sea a few years later after the deckload shifted. Fortunately, no lives were lost.
    - Dogfish caught in twine, August 23, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Dogfish caught in twine. Dogfish were a constant headache for fishermen as they had no commercial use and voraciously ate nearly every other species.
    - Approaching storm on Georges Bank, February 28, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Miss Judith coming into Point Jude, June 18, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Martha Porter coming home from a trip gillnetting, February 18, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Martha Porter coming home from a trip gillnetting. She also lobsters when appropriate.
    - Tomatuck heading out to her lobster traps on a brutally cold day in February, February 13, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Tomatuck heading out to her lobster traps on a brutally cold day in February. Note the ice covered breakwater in the background.
    - The Elizabeth Helen trawling with company outside of Block Island on a day trip groundfishing, June 11, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The Elizabeth Helen trawling with company outside of Block Island on a day trip groundfishing. This vessel was lost at sea a few years later after the deckload shifted. Fortunately, no lives were lost.
    - An unidentified lobster boat heads to sea with a load of traps to place, May 8, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - R.G. Billings fishing alone on the David D just off the Rhode Island coastline, June 11, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      R.G. Billings fishing alone on the David D just off the Rhode Island coastline. All vessels were sailing shorthanded from the port by this time as the fisheries declined. Fishing alone is quite dangerous, but by this time, many small boats followed this practice to eek out what living they could.
    - Perseverance heading out, January 9, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Perseverance heading out, January 9, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Scandinavian trawling just off the beach just outside of the Harbor of Refuge, May 8, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Commercial and private vessels in parade formation for the annual Blessing of the Fleet, July 28, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - An unidentified vessel returns to port, February 13, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Iron Horse heading to Georges Bank for squid, January 9, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Harvest Moon scalloping off Block Island, April 25, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Harvest Moon scalloping off Block Island. The dredge is hoisted high as John Fish adjusts the rig to tow better. John was just starting to experiment with this fishery (he normally lobsters for a living) and was having troubles getting the dredge to tow properly. John Fish (left) unidentified crew (right).
    - Sorting fish at sunset as they pass by on the conveyor on Vic Ter Rae on Georges Bank. Dennis Dimon (left) Lewis Dimon (right), March 1, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Heather Lynn coming home from a trip to Georges Bank, August 20, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Atlantic Queen tied up to her dock, August 22, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Atlantic Queen tied up to her dock. She was the largest of the fiberglass trawlers in the port. Beyond this size, steel is more economical and better suited to handling the stress involved in pulling large nets.
    - Linda Marie heads out to sea through the west gap for a day of trawling beyond Block Island while sports fishermen cast for stripers and blues off the west wall, May 8, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Ocean State and other vessels in parade formation during the Blessing of the Fleet, July 28, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - R.G. Billings fishing alone on the David D just off the Rhode Island coastline, June 11, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      R.G. Billings fishing alone on the David D just off the Rhode Island coastline. All vessels were sailing shorthanded from the port by this time as the fisheries declined. Fishing alone is quite dangerous, but by this time, many small boats followed this practice.
    - The Charlotte G returns in heavy weather from a trip to Georges Bank groundfishing, January 8, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Little Joe heads to sea in May for a day of lobstering as the deck crew fixes gear, May 25, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - The Lucy M drops a pair of wreaths on the outgoing tide in remembrance of fishermen lost at sea from Point Judith, July 28, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The Lucy M drops a pair of wreaths on the outgoing tide in remembrance of fishermen lost at sea from Point Judith. 2007th Blessing of the Fleet.
    - A man quahogging on the pond above Point Judith, March 14, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Cody hauled on a railway opposite Point Jude for painting and repair, April 16, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Cody hauled on a railway opposite Point Jude for painting and repair. This facility closed shortly after because new environmental regulations made the operation too costly to continue. The shipyard was turned into a yachting center, the fate of most waterfront facilities now.
    - Loud mouthed local gull, March 26, 2005, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - A grey day on Georges Bank, March 2, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Jake Everich hauling one of Tom Hoxsie's traps form a skiff, August 20, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Net reel covered on a trawler crossing an area closed to fishing, March 2, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Net reel covered on a trawler crossing an area closed to fishing. Regulations once forced trawlers to steam all the way around closed areas, but due to cost and time involved, the government eventually allowed trawlers to cover their twine and maintain a high speed while crossing these areas instead. On this trip, heavy wind began to tear the cover off. When fishermen stopped to fix the problem, the vessel was immediately contacted by the government to see what they were doing in a restricted area, as all commercial vessels are tracked 24/7 by the government. Fishermen joke there are more people in government watching fishermen than there are fishermen - something that may be true...
    - James Nelson on the Deborah Lee on a bait fishing trip for skate off Block Island, August 23, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Scandinavian trawling just off the beach just outside of the Harbor of Refuge, May 8, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Linda Marie heads for the west gap on her way groundfishing off Block Island, May 8, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Luann, a small, wooden eastern rig dragger tied to the dock, her fishing days over, August 23, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Yankee Pride returns to port, August 23, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Yankee Pride returns to port. Many of the vessel's names in the port reflect fishermen's feelings towards the job they do or are the names of women important in their lives - mothers, wives, and daughters.
    - Ocean State trawling off of Block Island, July 11, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Ocean State returns to her dock after unloading her catch from the day, February 13, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Offshore lobsterboat Karen Elizabeth returns from a five day trip to sea, May 25, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Wendy Gail heads east along the coast to her lobster pots, May 31, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Local mermaid attending the Blessing of the Fleet ceremonies, July 31, 2005, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - North Star tends her trap on the west wall, May 25, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      North Star tends her trap on the west wall. Sam Willis repairs gear in the skiff while Jake Everich and Tom Hozsie sort fish just landed. Left to right: Sam Willis, Jake Everich, Tom Hozsie.
    - Lewis Dimon V waits at the rail to hook gear accidentally lost overboard on a grey day on Georges Bank, January 28, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Sam Willis relashes a section of twine on the west wall trap, January 28, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Another local mermaid attending the Blessing of the Fleet, July 31, 2005, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - A cascade of saltwater hits the deck as the net is reeled in, October 2, 2006, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      A cascade of saltwater hits the deck as the net is reeled in. This is why fishermen wear foul weather gear when on deck, regardless of weather.
    - Lewis Dimon V directs a jet of water while cleaning the deck after sorting the last haul, January 28, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Lewis Dimon V directs a jet of water while cleaning the deck after sorting the last haul. The decks are constantly washed with high pressure hoses to keep them clean and less slippery for crew working on them.
    - View of a companion trawler on Georges Bank through the salt stained window of the pilothouse, October 4, 2006, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      View of a companion trawler on Georges Bank through the salt stained window of the pilothouse. Fishermen must pay constant attention while on the Bank due to the other boats trawling nearby.
    - Excaliber heading to Georges Bank, March 30, 2005, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Excaliber heading to Georges Bank
    - A fisherman attaches the doors to the trawl in rough weather, January 28, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Jameson Risser, captain of Timber Wolf, bags herring in the snow to be used as bait on their next offshore lobster trip, January 28, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - A huge bag of fish comes aboard during a blizzard on Georges Bank, January 28, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Butterfish, June 11, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - A lobsterboat heads out to tend her traps in the winter along the shoreline as an offshore trawler returns from a five day trip to Georges Bank, February 13, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - The Little Mermaid jammed in a window in the pilothouse aboard Njord, January 17, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Skate and a monkfish - not the teeth in the monkfish's mouth, August 23, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Rayda Cheramie returns from an offshore trip, February 13, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Trudy S returning from her lobster traps, August 7, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Charlotte G tied to her dock, January 8, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Oceania, a stainless steel gillnetter coming into the harbor, May 8, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Stacy Dziekan sorting fish on the Mikhela Louise on an offshore trip for squid, February 28, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Stacy Dziekan sorting fish on the Mikhela Louise on an offshore trip for squid. Stacy also served as cook aboard the vessel. In Pt. Judes' peak, trawlers carried a separate man as cook and large crews, but by this time crew had shrunk to the minimum size and fishermen shared all duties. Seen through the waterproof doorway leading into the cabins.
    - Karin & Linda comes in ahead of Kate & Sean, another small trawler after a day's fishing, May 30, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Pinup calendar in galley area aboard a trawler, February 28, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Pinup calendar in galley area aboard a trawler. As wives and children often come aboard vessels when in port, most artwork is more restrained than it had been in the past.
    - A fisherman works on deck in very heavy weather, lashing gear down to keep it from rolling across the deck, February 26, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - James Nelson working at the Black Rock trap, May 31, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Amelia Bucolo steams by the Lucy M on her way back to the docks after tending her trap, August 7, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - A skate, kept for lobster bait, sits on a boat's conveyor, August 23, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      A skate, kept for lobster bait, sits on a boat's conveyor. With larger skates, the "wings" are cut off for food.
    - Nautilus in the Harbor of Refuge, July 3, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - North Star at her west wall trap, May 7, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Isabella Rose coming home from a day trip groundfishing off Block Island, July 26, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Peter Nicholson, owner and captain of Njord, and Anthony Richards, his crewmember, look into the dredge as it washes before bringing it aboard, January 18, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Peter Nicholson, owner and captain of Njord, and Anthony Richards, his crewmember, look into the dredge as it washes before bringing it aboard. This was a scalloping trip outside of Long Island. Peter Nicholson (left) Anthony Richards (right).
    - Lobsters waiting to be measured and banded aboard the Capt. Robert, July 3, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Salted pogies to be used as bait on a lobster boat, July 3, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Salted pogies to be used as bait on a lobster boat. Pogies, herring, and skate are the most commonly used bait fish for lobsters in Point Judith.
    - Dogfish caught in twine, August 23, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Heather Lynn and Iron Horse tied to the dock, April 18, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Empty plastic bait barrel and dock gin pole used to lower bait to the deck of the boat, August 7, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Beautiful Atlantic salmon pulled from trap, May 10, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Beautiful Atlantic salmon pulled from trap - after photographing this fish, it was released back into the wild.
    - While fierce looking, this whiting is too small to do much damage to fishermen, September 4, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Net reels on the stern of the Elizabeth Helen, April 2, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Net reels on the stern of the Elizabeth Helen. This vessel was lost at sea just a few years after this photo was taken, fortunately, no lives were lost when she overturned.
    - Karin & Linda comes in ahead of Kate & Sean, another small trawler after a day's fishing, May 30, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Jesus Nievus working the trap at Black Rock, January 9, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - The Fishermen's Memorial, built to honor fishermen lost at sea, July 27, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The Fishermen's Memorial, built to honor fishermen lost at sea. At the time of the photo, there were 56 names of men lost at sea from Point Judith engraved on the memorial.
    - A lobster boat approaches the dock, August 7, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      A lobster boat approaches the dock. Note the open transom design, which allows traps to slide off the back deck without having to be lifted. Other fishing ports don't use open transoms and lift each trap to the rail to launch it.
    - Starfish and skates, March 30, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Barnacle encrusted lobster on deck, May 2, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Restless heads out to trawl on a foggy day, May 10, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Restless heads out to trawl on a foggy day. She is typical of small trawlers built in the 40s and 50s in Noank, Ct.
    - Jerry Babcock on the Deborah Lee, October 31, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Jerry Babcock on the Deborah Lee. This trip was to catch skate to be used as lobster bait. The bait was sold to The Bait Company on the Pt. Jude waterfront, who in turn sold it to local lobstermen. Block Island is in the background.
    - Harvest Moon heads out on a lobstering trip in the fog, August 7, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - David D trawling along the Rhode Island coast, June 11, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Two trawlers pass each other on Georges Bank on a calm day, February 28, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - A flatfish swims to the surface inside a fishtrap, looking for a way out, May 10, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Stacy Dziekan hooks up the doors to the net before launching them, March 1, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - An eastern rig heads to the fishing grounds, July 3, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      An eastern rig heads to the fishing grounds. Only a handful of these big steel eastern rigs still fish, most out of New Bedford, MA.
    - Slacker trawling off Block Island, April 25, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Lena Pearl returning home from an offshore trip, June 11, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Saretta fishing with the Newport bridge in the background, July 3, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Day trawler docks with much of the fleet at home, July 6, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Linda Marie comes in ahead of Isabella Rose after a day trawling off Block Island, March 14, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Flounder are stored white side up to make them look the best they can before reaching the fish buyers, January 13, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - James Nelson and Alan Glidden working on the Black Rock trap, May 31, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Kelsi & Morgan heads into the harbor after a day of fishing for skate to be used as bait. The boat will stop and unload the fish at The Bait Company, August 7, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Seagulls sweep in towards the stern of the vessel during the night in hope of stealing some fish, February 28, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Anthony Richards pushes the tongue of the scallop dredge down to the deck after landing the whole rig on deck, January 18, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Anthony Richards pushes the tongue of the scallop dredge down to the deck after landing the whole rig on deck. He will then hook the main winch to the bag to raise and dump the scallops onto the deck for sorting.
    - Lightning Bay coming into her dock, February 23, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Ellen Schomer on the Rebecca Mary on a day trip groundfishing in Block Island Sound, January 13, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Ellen Schomer on the Rebecca Mary on a day trip groundfishing in Block Island Sound. The trip was cut short after tearing their net - the tear too big to repair at sea. This was one of Ellen's last trips after 30 years at sea.
    - Carl Granquist on the Deborah Lee fishing for skate in Block Island Sound, March 30, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Carl Granquist on the Deborah Lee fishing for skate in Block Island Sound. Chris owns Restless, a small wooden trawler, but often works as a deckhand on other vessels to supplement his days at sea. (Fishermen can only fish a certain number of days on a license, so many fish for others when their days are limited.)
    - Dean West on the Grandville Davis fishing in Block Island Sound, June 11, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Roland "Bucky" Smith ices down fish on the Amilia Bucolo as she heads back to port, July 6, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Roland "Bucky" Smith ices down fish on the Amilia Bucolo as she heads back to port.
    - Seth Fletcher on the deck of Tradition on a daylong groundfishing trip outside of Block Island, March 15, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Michael Hopkins unloading the day's catch from the Rebecca Mary., March 14, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Michael Hopkins unloading the day's catch from the Rebecca Mary. The canvas bucket is lowered into the hold where others fill it with fish sorted by species. It is then dumped into the hopper at the end of the conveyor system to Mike's right.
    - A welder repairs a heavy steel door. A pair of doors are used to spread the wings of the towed net apart, August 22, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Seth Fletcher on the deck of Tradition on a daylong groundfishing trip outside of Block Island, March 15, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - St. Jude at her dock, August 20, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Peter Nicholson looks at the scallop dredge coming aboard the Njord, January 18, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Lena Pearl rests at her dock as Miss Trudy heads to work, March 14, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Mike Marchetti at the helm of the Captain Robert lobster fishing in Block Island Sound, April 25, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Scott Babcock at the helm of the Rebecca Mary on a groundfishing trip outside of Block Island, January 13, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Suzanne Beth at the dock, July 31, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Suzanne Beth at the dock. This vessel was a hybrid design - built like an Eastern rig with the high bow and working deck in the center of the vessel, but with a stern reel aft. After hauling, the full net was dragged forward to the center of the vessel for sorting - an attempt to keep the fishermen protected from heavy weather. Unfortunately, on the first voyage, a young crewmember was accidentally wound up in the net and killed, and fishermen never really liked the vessel after that. As an experiment, it never really seemed to work. She was later sold to New Bedford and converted to scalloping.
    - A pilot whale breaks the surface on Georges Bank, February 28, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Hope & Sydney at the docks, August 22, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Scott Babcock at the winch controls of the Rebecca Mary on a groundfishing trip outside of Block Island, January 13, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Scott Babcock at the winch controls of the Rebecca Mary on a groundfishing trip outside of Block Island. Here he lets the net out to the desired depth.
    - The Black Point Fish Trap Company truck, used to carry the Amelia Bucolo's day's catch back to the shipping area, April 23, 2007, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The Black Point Fish Trap Company truck, used to carry the Amelia Bucolo's day's catch back to the shipping area. Alan Glidden, who owns the company, made a business out of air-shipping seafood to the west coast, one of the first to employ air freighting of seafood.